All right, I reckon it's time we start
talking about the industrialization of
the United States and in this video
we'll consider the dizzying array of
technological innovations that made it
possible. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, so a major theme during this
period is the rapid industrialization of
the United States and that development
led to a metric buttload of changes
during this period. It quadrupled the
nation's gross domestic product which
measures the value of all the finished
goods a country produces. It also
fundamentally altered the relationships
between employers and workers. And we'll
discuss all of that ad nauseam in the
next couple of videos, but for now what
you really need to remember is that the
growth of industry resulted in the
dramatic increase in the production of
goods. And that happened because the
efficiency of manufacturing increased
thanks to new technologies and methods.
And then at the rise of the advertising
industry that generated desires in
consumers to buy all those goods and
that's how America got its big boy
industrial pants on. And all of this was
connected to the market revolution that
we discussed in unit four. That was
industrialization 1.0, but during the
Gilded Age we got industrialization 2.0.
Now, before I tell you about a couple of
the technologies and natural resources
that made all this possible, I want to
give you an example that really ties all
these themes together. And that example,
my dear pupil, is Jell-O. Oh yes, that
sweet artificially colored jiggly
goodness is a perfect illustration of a
mass-produced good that was only
possible thanks to the rapid
industrialization of America. So, first
of all, in case you don't know, Jell-O
is made from gelatin which is a protein
found in the skin and ligaments and
bones of animals like pigs and cows. So,
as industrial food production was taking
off in the United States, what was
really important in those factories was
the meat of the animal. In other words,
meat was the money maker. And so, all
the useless parts of the animal like the
tendons and skin and bones were just
trash. But apparently one day a guy
looked at that pile of nasty bloody
animal detritus and was like, "I bet I
can make a dessert out of that." And as
it turned out, he was right. So, as
factories became more efficient in their
production, some entrepreneurial types
figured out that all the waste generated
by the industrial process could also be
turned into a profitable venture. And
so, Jell-O was created as a way to
profit from what would otherwise be
trash. And thanks to the abundance of
marketing materials advertising the new
treat, its sales began to grow. Now, to
be fair, Jell-O wouldn't have its viral
moment into the 1950s, but it started in
the Gilded Age thanks to the rapid
advances in industrial production. Okay,
so now that we've had our dessert, let's
get to the main meal of this topic and
consider a couple technologies that
facilitated the rise of industry in the
United States during this period and
I'll give you three. First, the great
granddaddy of all technological
innovations during this period was the
expansion of railroads. Now, it's true
that railroads have been connecting the
United States for decades prior to this
period, but there were main three
significant problems to the full
economic integration of the American
continent via railroad. First, different
companies used different rail gauges for
their tracks which meant that a train
from one company couldn't necessarily
travel on a track laid by another
company. But during the Gilded Age,
railroad companies all agreed to adopt a
standard gauge rail which opened
railroads to all trains. Full economic
integration unlocked. Second, in order
to ship goods on trains across the
country with accuracy and efficiency,
strict timetables for departure and
arrival needed to be observed. However,
by the 1880s each town and city across
the country essentially set their own
time. So, during this period railroad
companies solved this problem by
creating four time zones across the
continent which standardized time and
made rail travel far more efficient and
productive. And then third, railroad
expansion was also facilitated by the
improvement of steel manufacture. And
this was thanks to the development of
the Bessemer process which was a
technique for creating stronger and
longer-lasting steel which in turn was
used to create better and more enduring
railroad. And don't forget that by the
end of the 19th century the United
States was connected by multiple
transcontinental railroads. And so, that
combined with the developments that I
just mentioned means that industrial
manufacturers could ship goods and
access raw materials all over the dang
country at speed and real cheap. Okay,
the second major technology you need to
know is the telegraph. recall from the
last unit that Samuel Morse introduced
the telegraph in 1844. During the Civil
War and the years after, thousands of
miles of telegraph wires were hung
across the United States and it had
become more and more a part of normal
daily life among Americans. But that led
to an even more significant development
in 1866 with the opening of a
transatlantic telegraph cable connecting
the United States to Europe. Like only
50 years before, to send a message
across the ocean required a ship to be
at sea for months, but now the same
communication could occur in minutes.
And that didn't just mean that Americans
and Europeans could chat about whatever
was on their minds. this actually had
the effect of creating an international
market for basic goods like coal and oil
and steel and grain. And that trend only
sped up with the introduction of the
telephone in 1876 which was invented by
our boy Alexander Graham Bell. And then
the third technology that facilitated
the growth of industry was the
introduction of electricity. It was
Thomas Edison who was responsible for
many of the technologies that
revolutionized business during this
period, but arguably it was the
incandescent lightbulb and the adoption
of electricity that topped them all. You
see, the lightbulb was adopted in homes
across the nation as well as factories
and businesses. And in this way, work
could continue after the world became
dark and that led to enormous increases
in productivity. But lightbulbs needed
electricity and so did a host of other
electrical innovations like streetcars.
Therefore, Edison opened the first
central electricity generator in New
York City in 1882. And so, electricity
fostered increases in industrial
productivity for the very simple reason
that it was a more reliable source of
power than steam power or water power
before. But of equal importance to the
growth of industry during this period
was increased access to natural
resources. So, because of the rapid pace
of westward migration during this
period, most of the western United
States had been at least marginally
settled by 1890. And that meant much
easier access to the abundant natural
resources that lay buried beneath the
western soil, particularly coal and oil.
Or if you're from the South like me,
coal and oil. Anyway, the large-scale
availability and extraction of coal
induced many industries to convert their
operations from water power to steam
power which was a much more reliable
source of energy. Additionally, the
large deposits of petroleum in the West
created entire industries all on its
own. For example, the process of
refining petroleum led to the production
of a much more efficient lubricant for
factory machines. And then the
byproducts of petroleum refining yielded
kerosene which replaced whale oil and
wood as the chief natural resource for
generating heat. And I could go on
flapping my mouth hole about all the
developments and technologies that
facilitated American industrialization,
but we'll have to pick up that story in
the next video. All right, click here to
watch my other videos from unit six or
you can click here to grab my video note
guides which will help you get all the
contents in this course firmly crammed
into your brain fold. I'm glad you came
around and I'll catch on the flip-flop.
I'm blur out.